It actually felt in some ways like
Instagram was dying.
>> This is Ryan Olsen. He grew to a
principal engineer or IC8 at Instagram
in just a few years. One promo per half
or two halves straight. What was that
like?
>> I was like, "Hey, I think I got misleled
and I think you should promote me from
four to six in this cycle."
>> As the lead iOS engineer on Instagram
stories, he shared what it was like
behind the scenes.
>> The CTO and co-founder Mike Kger, he was
like, "You know what? Don't don't worry
about trying to AB test this thing.
Build and ship it.
>> Do you think that the company would be
better off if you just like laid off
half the people?
>> Even if it's a random selection, do
things go better and frequently we felt
like, yeah, maybe.
>> In 2011, I understand that you you
interviewed for Facebook and and you
failed. Can you talk through that
experience and what that was like? I
thought Facebook was super cool at the
time. Um, I wanted it so bad. And uh I
was just incredibly nervous. Like um I I
remember the uh interviewer, he kind of
asked the question. He's like, "Oh, you
can just do it on my machine." He turned
around his laptop, pushed it over to me.
I put my hands on the keyboard. You
could actually hear like the the keys
like rattling because I was shaking so
bad, which just, you know, it starts
this feedback loop. um hearts pounding
and uh the question that he asked was
actually one that ended up getting
banned at Facebook um which I feel some
uh somewhat better about but um
>> what was the question? It was this
engram buckets question which yeah
there's like a very simple solution if
you know data structures um where use a
dictionary um and that solution didn't
come to me so I wrote this like
horrendous triple nested for loop um I
mean it was definitely like you know the
interview went quite poorly and yeah so
he he actually cut the interview short
which as as an interviewer that's like
something I would never do um even if
somebody's was failing like you want to
you want to try to have a good candidate
experience. Um and so he cut it short
and he was just like look you you you're
just not going to be able to make it at
Facebook. Um which was like kind of a
knife to the heart like I I you know I
wanted this thing so bad and then this
guy is just like yeah you're just not
good enough for this. Um and it actually
took me like I was really down from that
for for a while. It took me a while to
kind of like bounce back uh after that.
Luckily I did bounce back. I feel like I
I I had a pretty good good career at
Facebook, so I managed to managed to
prove him wrong. I I I never got the
name of the interviewer. Um, so I I have
no idea who it was, but Yeah.
>> Yeah. Well, I mean, that to me shows how
broken the interview process is. If I
mean, you're an incredibly high
performer and if you are not getting
through it, then clearly it's not, you
know, testing for the right things.
>> Yeah. I've always I've always struggled
actually with like the the lead code
style um interview and and uh it was
something I was always interested in
trying to change while at Facebook but
um it you know it's the interview
process there is such a such a machine
across a big company. Um it's one of the
things I enjoy about having my own
company is like you know I don't have to
do those things that I don't agree with.
And so after failing that Facebook
interview, I understand that you went to
go work at a startup named Flipboard and
you were an intern, one of four interns.
What was that experience like working at
Flipboard?
>> Yeah, so um I'll tell a little bit more
of the in between story there. Um I a
couple months after the Facebook
interviewed
with Amazon um and uh it was a phone
interview, so I was actually a lot more
comfortable. Um I did well on that. how
I got the offer. Uh they did the kind of
exploding offer. It was like, you know,
I got a call on Friday. It was like, you
need to tell us by Monday if you're
taking this or not. Um and I was
prepared to take it. Seemed like a cool
cool opportunity. I had a an investor
friend. He um founded Insight Partners,
which is one of the big uh venture
firms. and um he had mentioned at some
point in the past he's like you know at
some point maybe I'll connect you with
with some startups and so I just reached
out to him and I said hey you know I'm I
got this intern offer at Amazon I think
I'm going to take it and he was like
don't take it yet like let me connect
you with some startup people um so it
was on a Sunday and he um sent an email
connecting me with uh the co-founder of
Flipboard this guy Evan Well, Evan
called me right away and I actually I
didn't really want to pick up the phone
cuz I was like, "Oh man, I I don't want
to do another interview and um kind of
just want to take this job offer that I
have." Um but I'm very glad I picked up
the phone. Um and I had a great
conversation with Evan. He uh he had
worked at Apple on kind of the core of
iOS. Um he actually wrote UI view
controller which is you know like the
the core kind of UI uh class that you
interact with and uh he had also taught
this course at Stanford um called CS
193P which they made available on iTunes
and that was how I learned iOS
development. I I took it a different
year that Evan didn't teach. Um, but we
had a really good conversation about
that and uh, so after that phone call I
was like, "Yeah, okay. This this makes
sense. Like this this just seems way
more interesting than whatever I'm going
to do at at Amazon." So I went there in
the summer and the company was about 50
people at that time and I think yeah, we
had like maybe four interns or so. Um,
and it was just a a an extremely high
density of talent like uh people were
all super smart. Um, they come from
these backgrounds, you know, like
writing the iOS frameworks at Apple. Um,
the one of the other interns that I sat
next to, he he wasn't really an intern.
He had worked at Apple and he was
actually doing a medical degree and he
just needed a job for the summer. He was
friends with Evan. So, um, but he had
written the push notifications framework
and he was talking about like how he set
that up for the demo at WWC and it was
like running off his like Mac Mini just
in Moscone where they had the conference
and um and another story he told was uh
he had written like the um kind of clock
framework, the clock app and they had a
bad time zone bug one year for I think
it was around New years or something and
they screwed up and like people's alarms
didn't go off and was like fairly
catastrophic. Um, and it's like yeah,
actually make making sure people's
alarms go off is pretty important. Um,
so yeah, it was just a really really
good learning environment and I learned
a ton about iOS and about building
product. Two of the other interns um
have gone on to to make multi-billion
dollar companies. Um, one is Dylan Field
who founded Figma, which went public
yesterday. I think it's a $50 billion
market cap today. Um, he actually he was
an intern through the first half of the
summer that I was there and then um he
ended his internship and he founded
Figma then. Um, so um yeah, that that it
it was it was cool. People were kind of
into startups, entrepreneurial. Um, I
actually really questioned whether I
should go back to finish my last year of
school. I'm ultimately glad that I did,
but it felt like there was just this
moment happening. I was like, I can't
leave. I I have to stay here and um if
if I go back to school, I'm going to
miss out on on something really
critical.
>> So, Dylan Field, co-founder of Figma, is
one of the interns. And I saw in your
writing the other intern was Devon Fin
Fininser who's like founder of OpenC
which is also at some point it was
billion dollar. I don't know the exact
valuation now but that is that is
absurd. Were there any traits that you
noticed in those people or that intern
class that kind of foreshadowed that
they would be that successful?
>> They were definitely determined to start
companies. it was like that was what
they wanted to do. And I think that was
a bit different than what I saw, you
know, from like my university
classmates. People just wanted to get a
job, you know, kind of like the highest
aspiration was like to work at a big
tech company. Um, and both Devon and
Dylan were like, you know, we want to
start companies. And there was a lot of
talk about ideas and and what they would
do. It's interesting to think back of
back to the early days of Figma or you
know like talking to Dylan around that
time. I think the idea that they had
they they weren't totally landed on the
idea but they had this one really
interesting insight which was WebGL was
this new technology that was really
going to enable new things on the web.
And Dylan's co-founder Evan was a really
talented engineer and was like very
early to WebGL and very skilled at that.
Um, and I think they went through some
different iterations of the product that
weren't really tailored toward designers
at all. Like they Dylan had talked about
how they were a meme generator app for a
week or something like that. Yeah. I
mean, so I think it took them a bit to
to find exactly kind of their use case
and their customer base. Um, but they
they had this vision of like this
technology is really going to change
things and they stuck with that and uh
it's it's cool cool to see how how far
they came.
>> Yeah. It seems like while you were
working at Flipboard, you built a a
successful open- source project and you
know, yeah, some of the first commits
are in 2014. I'm curious what's the
story behind that and why did you open
source that? So during my internship, I
did some work on just kind of internal
debugging tools for our iOS app. And um
it was the it was the first time I'd
really worked deeply in Objective C. And
I found the language really interesting
because it's a compiled language, but it
has this dynamic aspect. It has this
runtime that exposes actually quite a
bit of information. you know while the
app is running you can inspect a lot of
things about um what are the classes
what are the methods on those classes
you can call them dynamically you can
see all the state all the properties and
uh so the first kind of iteration of
that was just building a tool to kind of
inspect the state of the app and and
tweak it um on demand I think we called
it tweaker it was FL tweaker um and I
just kind of continued iterating on that
um as like a side project. I mean my
main you know we were a startup so we
had probably between three to five
people on the iOS team through through
most of my time there and so mostly I
was building Flipboard, building the
app, building new features. Um so it was
kind of like a nights and weekends thing
that I was working on this debugging
tool and uh people in the company found
it really useful. It was just um yeah a
way to kind of like understand what was
going on in the app under the hood. Um
you could see all the network requests,
you could see what was on the file
system. I kind of asked, hey, can I open
source this? I think it's like going to
be useful for for other people. And um
everyone was on board with that. So we
pushed it out and uh yeah, it's it's
become um one of the more popular iOS
debugging tools. I think a lot of a lot
of apps use it. definitely used it uh
Facebook and Instagram. It's It was also
cool to see it. It took on kind of a
life of its own. So, I've been less
active as a maintainer of it in the past
probably probably really since I started
Instagram. Uh maybe a couple years into
that. Uh but this guy Tanner really took
it over and um has continued evolving it
and adding features.
>> That's awesome. Um, I remember hearing
about Flex at Instagram as well. So, I
wasn't aware that that was actually
something you'd built before you were at
the company, which is really cool. I'm
curious, did building something like
that and open sourcing it have some
unexpected, you know, butterfly effect
on your career in some way?
>> In some ways it did. In some ways, I
thought maybe it would have more um
impact than than it did. So an example
of that is um when I came to interview
at Instagram uh I had already released
this open source and so I was like you
know here's here's my code you want to
see what I can do like this is a thing
that I built that you can go look at and
and none of my interviewers had any
interest in in in looking at it you know
they were like we want to know if you
can do this phone number sorting thing
um and so that was like pretty
frustrating to me I was like you know
you you can see my work here and you and
you choosing not to look at it. Other
people who are kind of slightly outside
of the interview loop but part of the
recruiting process um like uh Jonathan
Dan was this guy who worked at uh
Facebook on the iOS team. He kind of I
think he actually did the file new
project in Xcode for the Facebook iOS
app. Um, so he'd kind of started that
and uh he was the one who who got me to
interview in the first place and and
that was all through him seeing this
tool and what it could do and yeah and I
think he advocated in the candidate
review or whatever cuz I I think I had
kind of a mixed mixed interview loop. Um
yeah, I mentioned before like I was uh
was very nervous in my in my uh
internship interview. Um, and uh the I
did something for my full-time interview
that um it's maybe helpful to to some
people out there uh that get nervous in
interview situations. Um there's
something called beta blockers which uh
they they block adrenaline. So when you
have kind of the physical effects of
being nervous like pounding heart or you
know sweaty palms, that type of thing,
you can start to feel those and and it
can create this feedback loop where you
kind of spiral down and really starts to
like block your performance. Um and so
what a beta blocker does is it just
stops that adrenaline from firing and so
you can kind of stay calm and never end
up in that spiral. So, um, I got a
prescription for that for for my
interview, um, interview
performance-enhancing drugs, I guess,
and, uh, and I took that and it was very
helpful for me. So, I was able to to
stay calm. Um, I think performers
sometimes use this, uh, you know,
comedians or whatever, um, just to to
kind of like, you know, be able to stay
themselves and not um, end up in this in
this nervous loop. So I did that, but
you know, I was still like kind of elite
code style interview loop, which which I
um don't do that well at. So I think I
had like a few like absolute confidence
hire uh interviews and probably a few no
hires. Um somehow I managed to to get
through. Um but I think that also
contributed to I came into to Facebook
as a IC4. Um I guess one level up from
new grad engineer and um I would say
like I was underleveled higher. I think
you know part of that would have came
from my interview loop. And when you use
the beta blockers, I'm curious, is it
basically completely removed the nerves
component for you or is it just kind of
like helps a little bit?
>> I've only used them a handful of times.
Um, but it pretty much completely, you
know, like no noticeable kind of nervous
effects. I mean, I think you can still
be in your head for sure about um what
you're saying, but um it takes away a
lot of those physical effects. Um, so no
no pounding hard or or you know
sweating, that type of thing.
>> After you passed the interview for
full-time, you started working on the
Instagram team working on iOS and I'm
curious what the what the environment
was like at the time. You know, what was
the size of the team?
>> Um, yes. So I came in and I think there
were about 10 iOS engineers working on
Instagram then. Um, which was actually
the team size had come down. So the the
way the story's been told to me is um
there were maybe about 20 iOS engineers
and there was kind of this internal war
over um the direction of the the
codebase like the infrastructure how how
the Instagram iOS app would be built.
And there was a really talented uh iOS
engineer uh Scott Goodson who was
managing the team and he had made this
framework for the Facebook paper app
called Async Display Kit and it was kind
of a different approach towards how you
manage um writing iOS. Uh, and I guess
there were kind of like waring factions
like some people were, you know, very
pro async display kit and other people
were like, "No, we should just stick to
vanilla iOS, how Apple builds apps." The
way it was told to me is like these two
factions like they fought each other and
they destroyed each side destroyed each
other. Everyone just left and nobody
won. So, um, so I came into kind of like
this uh this team. I mean, I got to I I
feel like not many engineers had been
there more than, you know, 6 months to a
year. It was like a pretty new team.
Um, and because of that, there was
actually like a lot of lowhanging fruit.
Um, a lot of places to to have impact.
One of the first things I did was just
to put the app into uh a tool called the
time profiler. Most iOS developers will
will know this in Xcode. um or in
instruments um and just looked at you
know okay what is happening on cold
start and there was a bunch in in kind
of the startup path there was a bunch of
work happening for the profile tab which
you know many people will never tap into
and um if they do you can kind of do
that work at that time so it was like a
very easy win to shave 20% off our cold
start time just by deferring that work
until later. Another example was we had
this networking library uh AF networking
and there's something um I mean I guess
most programmers are familiar with
assertions
um in iOS the way assertions are
typically handled is it's something that
you run when the app is in debug mode to
kind of crash and and alert you to a
problem. uh but you kind of have
fallback behavior for production and you
don't actually crash the app and so this
networking library was building being
built with assertions on and it was
crashing the app for like benign
failures like a network failure right
where the app could recover we were just
crashing um and so that cut our crash
rate by 80%. Um and uh you know it was
just like a one on one line change just
NS block assertions but it's a pretty
significant impact on on the functioning
of the app. Uh and we uh Instagram had
this this cool tradition uh where every
week they would give what was called the
axe and it wasn't getting fired which it
sounds like um if you got the axe it was
like you did something of outsiz impact.
Um, and it was actually across all
functions. Didn't have to be
engineering, could be product, design,
whatever. And so for that 80% crash,
crash reduction. I won the axe. And um
it was this big physical axe uh that you
got to carry around for a week. At
first, I thought you got to take like I
was like, "Oh, I get this axe."
>> Yeah.
>> I had it at my desk for a week and I was
like, "Oh, no. There's just one axe.
Somebody else is going to get it next
week." Um but yeah,
>> I remember the axe. What's the story
behind that? Is that something the
Instagram founders like had done?
>> At some point, they had been asked by
like GQ or some men's magazine to do
like a holiday gift guide and I think
they just kind of came up with like
random gifts and um one of them was like
they found this service that was making
like bespoke axes.
you you could get this axe. And then one
of their investors like read that
article and then they sent them this
huge axe. Um, and apparently Facebook
security was like pretty unhappy about
this axe, this weapon in the office, so
they made them put it on a plaque. Uh,
it was like mounted to the plaque. You
couldn't take it off. Uh, but it was
Yeah, it was it was a cool tradition.
Um, you know, later, uh, in my time
there, they ended the axe as like a very
intentional thing. They were like, I
guess they thought people were feeling
excluded because it was like a weapon
that was being given or something like
that. But I I was kind of sad when that
happened cuz it felt like, you know, at
that time the founders were were gone
and it was like this piece of like early
Instagram culture that they were kind of
like sweeping under the rug. So,
>> so I guess going into your first major
project after all those lowh hanging
fruit, I understand there was a big
redesign of the Instagram app called
White Out. Can you talk about the story
behind that project?
>> Yeah, it was a couple months into my
time there and it kind of got word that
um we were working on a new icon which
ended up being very controversial. Um,
and as part of that, we were going to do
like this kind of uh redesign of the
app, a big visual refresh. And I don't
remember exactly what I did, but I
remember being like, I have to work on
this thing. This is like, this sounds so
cool. This is what I want to do. And,
you know, I told my manager, I was like
meeting the designers that were working
on it. Um, so I basically just
maneuvered myself in into working on
this project. And uh the the main
designer on it, Joy Vincent, um who was
just like yeah, just an incredible
talent and the nicest guy ever. Really
sad. He he passed away while we were at
Instagram. Um but um I sat in a war room
um you know just like a conference room
basically uh with him for I think
probably two or three months and just
every day we'd be like okay new screen
and app we'd go look at it. He'd be like
all right I want to do this this this
and I would do that and I' you know pass
the phone over to him and just back and
forth like that. Um, you know, we we did
kind of a whole new color palette for
the app, new icons. Um, and one of the
goals was to
really make all of the focus in
Instagram on the content on the photos
and the videos and to take all the color
out of the chrome. And it's basically,
you know, how Instagram looks today. But
at that time, you know, we had this kind
of dark blue and black chrome everywhere
in the app. and uh things were have a
lot heavier um and uh yeah so we just
tried to to really simplify it down and
make all the color come from the content
itself.
>> Was it a gated launch or was it a just
launch it all at once kind of project?
>> So AB testing was like pretty new at
Instagram at that point. Um you Facebook
was was doing a lot of it and Instagram
was kind of more the like oh we know
what's good so we'll just ship it. And
uh when I started working on on this
project, the the CTO and co-founder of
Mike Creger, he he was like, "You know
what? Don't don't worry about trying to
AB test this thing." He's like, "Just
just ship it. Like build it and ship
it." Um, and actually at that time like
they were still sort of using branching
as like a way to to build big features,
but I had seen some longived branches
uh like the the um direct messaging
feature had been built as a as a longive
branch and it was a nightmare merging it
back in because they branched off for
like 3 months and weren't really
rebasing and then they you know merge
this thing back in. It was it was I
think pretty awful and and this redesign
touched literally every surface of of
the app. Um so I was kind of like well
this is not going to be a good way to
build it. So I put it behind kind of a
feature flag and was constantly merging
it and had to build abstractions like
all the colors became semantic colors.
So you know um it's like instead of
saying that icon is black it's like it's
icon color or something like that. um or
it's disabled icon color and then you
could switch inside of that function for
you know are we on the new design or the
old design. Um and so that ended up
being just kind of a much easier way to
to build it incrementally. And then it
also actually opened up the possibility
of testing it. Um and so we we went to
to ship it and it was going to be just
like a 2% hold out. So, like, you know,
we were going to ship the new icon. Um,
it 98% of people were going to have the
new design and then we were just going
to have like 2% of people, you know,
with the old design just to make sure
that like nothing was was broken or
changed drastically. And uh I had
submitted the app to Apple. I I dropped
in the new icon. You know, we were ready
to go. People had champagne ready for
the launch party. And it was like the
night before we were supposed to to
launch this thing. And um someone kind
of in the Facebook executive ex
executive team above uh Instagram came
in and was like no you guys are not
doing this.
Um I guess they Facebook had had a
redesign that went poorly. Um and they
just saw this as the same thing and uh
and so they were like you need to run AB
tests of this up front. Um, so I I was
up at like 1:00 a.m. just like backing
things out and trying to like resubmit
the app to Apple and uh we we tested it.
I actually tested really well. Um was a
little bit sad because it kind of
crushed like the launch that we we had
planned. Um you know cuz then there are
all these articles about this new UI
that Instagram's maybe going to do. Um
but uh but yeah, I mean it all worked
out. Um but I I did have a a takeaway
from that which is like um I mean
testing definitely has a a place. It's
extremely useful even in our startup you
know we test things where you sometimes
get counterintuitive results um things
in our onboarding flow how people
convert on things um it's extremely
useful to run AB tests for that I think
for like highle product direction and
like what you want the thing to be I I
prefer to come in with a a stronger
opinion and not just kind of like um
look at the look at the data and only
let the the data guide the decisions.
Um, so I I think there's a risk if you
do too much experimentation that you get
trapped in kind of incrementalism.
So it's, you know, easy to get those 1%
wins, but you're never going to get that
50% uh jump.
>> On the major redesign case though, if
you just went for it though too, there's
also the other side risk though, right?
which is your product taste might be off
and people hate it and then it's a a
pain to come back.
>> Yeah. Yeah, for sure. Um I I think we we
had enough confidence I guess in in
using it. I mean it felt really good
internally and um I think at least on
the inter in kind of redesigning the
app, we we thought that would be good.
Um the icon was definitely a little bit
more controversial and then when we
shipped that people hated it. I mean it
was like I say it's the last time I
looked at Twitter after our product
launch because I went on and you know it
was supposed to be the celebratory day.
We had worked so hard on this thing. it
went out and we were just getting raked
on Twitter and uh yeah I mean it was it
was kind of sad but I think you know
change is hard. Um especially I think
people feel ownership over their home
screens and and all of a sudden this
thing just changed on them. Um and it
was kind of like a a little bit more of
a bleeding edge design direction too.
Like I think the the flat icon and the
gradient, you know, today feels very at
home, but at that time a lot of the
icons were pretty skephic and 3D. Yeah.
So so it was a bit rough. The the funny
other thing from that, you know, we
could see from the data actually that uh
this icon change uh it materially
improved how many people a day open the
app. Um, and we've actually seen this in
in um the app of my new company called
Retro, but actually like the icon uh can
impact whether people open the app like
how visible it is to them on on the
screen. So, it became more noticeable I
think amongst the other icons and people
actually uh tapped it more often. It
reminds me of I think some of Thomas
Dimson's work on the ranking versus
chronological
like the public perception is so
different from how actually people are
voting with their usage. Like people are
using it a lot more when it's when it's
ranked but you know for some reason
there's this like very vocal minority
that is saying I absolutely hate this.
>> Totally. Yeah. that that actually um the
feed ranking um shipped about the same
time as as this redesign and
uh I mean I was actually skeptical of it
as well. Um the the metric that changed
my mind on the ranking which I think the
story might be a little bit different
today but um at the time uh one of the
things that moved was actually how often
people shared to Instagram. So people
that had this uh feed ranking experience
were actually creating more themselves.
They were sharing more. Um and it was
partly because the feed ranking allowed
uh Instagram to show them their friends
more often. Um and so you saw content
from people like you and I think you
wanted to have that mutual connection so
you would actually share more yourself.
And so that kind of was an insight that
flipped it in my mind where, you know,
cuz people would say, "Oh, I'm just
using the app more because like you're
not showing me the things I want, so I'm
scrolling further or whatever." But I
was kind of like, "Okay, they're
actually like creating more content."
That that's kind of hard to dispute.
Like that's that's probably a good
thing. Um I I really liked uh kind of
the mission the original mission of
Instagram was like capture and share the
world's moments. And I I really liked it
as a way to kind of encourage people to
be creative and see beauty in the world.
And that was just a mission I felt like
I could get behind. And so something
like this where people were actually
creating more, I was like, "Okay, yeah,
that that that's probably a good thing."
I think at this leg of your career, I
think one thing that you wrote you wrote
about is that, you know, finding an
amazing designer was like a big part of
it for you. And so I'm curious, how did
you find the amazing designer that you
did work with and what makes a great
designer great?
>> Yeah, I've always just tried to, you
know, be be the engineer that like the
top designers want to work with. Um, and
yeah, it's just an incredible
opportunity if you work at these types
of companies where you can just have
their work kind of flow through you. Um,
be a part of it. Um so that for product
engineers that that's one piece of
advice I often give is like um your
impact can be multiplied so much by
finding a good designer and and creating
a really good working relationship with
them.
>> Is there a reason why you say
specifically the design function versus
the engineering function? Like imagine I
I identify some very senior engineer
that has some engineering design and I
just devote myself to it and kind of
attach to them. What's the difference
between doing that versus the really
talented designer? So I should make a
bit of a distinction between like if
you're in sort of a product engineering
um function where you're you're working
on like the features for users, the
interface kind of the front end then I
think like you know that's where you
really want to pair with a designer. If
you're in a more infrastructure role,
maybe the analogy is like finding that
really talented um super senior engineer
uh and and being the engineer they want
to work with. Um you know, they've got
great ideas and you can kind of
implement that. So yeah, probably
different depending on kind of uh what
role you have.
>> And so this white out project was in
2016. I'm kind of surprised in the same
year you also built stories with Tiger
Squad of some very famous people I'm
aware of. Can you tell me the story
about you know building stories for
Instagram?
>> Uh the redesign wrapped up and um I had
actually been kind of kicked off my my
uh previous team. Um right after I
joined they said we're moving the team
to New York. Do you want to move to New
York? And I was like no.
I I kind of I'm okay here in California.
They're like, "Okay, that's fine. Well,
you just have to find a new team." I was
like, "Okay, I I kind of wanted to be on
this team." Um so, um I kind of like
delayed it. I worked on this uh redesign
project and um then I joined the search
and explore team. Um, and I was only on
the team for a couple of weeks and a
friend of mine, um, who was also an iOS
engineer at the company decided to quit
and he had been working on what was
called the creation team and leading the
project that would become stories. And
uh my manager um was like, "Hey, you
know, this is actually a really
important effort for the company. Like,
I don't necessarily want you to lead my
team, but like I think this is a good
opportunity for you." And um I really
believed in in what this team was trying
to do. Um, at that time it it's sort of
surprising in hindsight given how big
Instagram is today, but it actually felt
in some ways like Instagram was dying
because a lot of the sort of everyday
sharing uh from people you knew, normal
people was evaporating. It was kind of
being replaced by creators and
influencers.
And uh some of that everyday sharing was
going to Snapchat which had this
ephemeral format. Um and so we were
tasked with just you know how do we get
kind of normal people to feel
comfortable sharing to Instagram again.
So I I went over to to lead the iOS team
on stories and
uh one of the first things we did after
I joined the team is we actually cut the
team size significantly. So there had
been a lot of people working on it. It
had been pretty churny. Um they had
tried different product directions. Uh a
lot of them didn't really feel that
great. They weren't working out. And in
some ways they were working on things to
have work for people to do um or or
there was just like not um not enough
space for the people that were there.
And we just decided, hey, we can
actually move a lot faster if we go down
to a smaller team. So, uh, it was myself
and one other iOS engineer was kind of
like the core team, and then we'd get
some help from other iOS engineers, two
Android engineers, and we didn't even
have a dedicated server engineer. It was
the infrastructure team, or like you can
have half a person. Um, it's half their
time. Uh, which, you know, for what
stories has become, it's it seems kind
of crazy. Uh, but it it really allowed
us to to move quickly. Um, you had
ownership over the whole thing. So, it's
never like a question of am I working on
something that someone else is working
on, am I going to step on their toes?
You know, if there's a bug, it's like,
okay, that's that's my bug. I got to go
fix it. And uh and there was less
discussion around decisions, we could
just make them more quickly. I say like
if you want to go fast, go small. Uh and
I'm a a strong believer in small teams
as like really the best way to operate.
Um it's definitely not the only way to
operate, but it's my preferred way. And
uh yeah, so we we went through that and
um we built it just over two to three
months. Was pretty quick. I
never worked so hard in my life. I was
working Yes. like 16 18 hour days, 7
days a week. Uh in the office every
weekend.
Yeah. I would like leave at like 1 or 2
a.m. to go home. I was driving back and
forth from San Francisco. I I was really
determined to not sleep in the office. I
was like, you know what? I'm always
going to go home, see my girlfriend. And
it was kind of silly because I was
spending this extra time driving. I
really should have just slept in the
office. Uh but um yeah, it was intense,
but it was fun. It felt like we were
building something really important and
we were using the product ourselves. We
were really enjoying it. It also was
like this bonding experience amongst
this small team. So our PM on the
project is now my co-founder at at my
company and
um you know I'm very close still with
with uh the other folks that worked on
it. And it also it felt in it's funny
because in some ways we were kind of the
incumbent to to Snapchat, but in other
ways they were very much winning in
terms of this kind of like everyday
sharing. And so we actually kind of felt
like the underdog. We we had a poster
up, a Ghostbusters poster up in our our
war room. Um, and yeah, just it felt
like we were kind of um in this in this
war against them and uh and I thought,
you know, maybe we maybe we could win.
>> What was it in your opinion that like
when you look at those two products,
what was it that the Instagram version
was doing so much better than the
Snapchat one? Yeah, I think we we had a
sort of unfair advantage in that people
already had their friend grafted on
Instagram
and the people that they wanted to share
with, but we just kind of weren't giving
them the right outlet um to to actually
do that sharing. And so as soon as we
had that, I think it really stopped the
outward flow um to to go to Snapchat for
that type of sharing. Um you know, I
think we also did push the the format
forward. Um certainly Snapchat deserves
all the credit for coming up with this
container that was a lot more
comfortable. Um you know, it's kind of
24-hour, the content doesn't stick
around forever. um full screen immersive
all those things. Uh but at the time
there was like a lot uh that exists in
both stories products today that was not
there in Snapchat. So um you know even
be able to navigate backwards by tapping
left on the screen like that didn't
exist. So I think we brought a lot of
nice touches like that. Uh the hold to
pause something I mentioned in the
career notes. So, you know, I was using
this early version that we had built and
these things were autoplay and they were
kind of going by too quickly and just
like intuitively put my thumb on the
screen and wanted to pause it and it
didn't pause. So, I was like, "Oh, I can
just do that." So, then I I built the
hold to pause and you know, now that
just feels like a core part of the
navigation and and the format. Um so
yeah that that's another uh thing like
when I mentor engineers um I mean you
just have this power as an engineer to
just build your ideas like if you are
using something and you think it should
work a different way you can just go do
that and that's that's such an awesome
thing. Um, and so, uh, I encourage, you
know, for sure product engineers, it's
like if you have ideas, just just build
them and put them out and have people
try them. And, uh, it's it's such a cool
thing to be able to do.
>> It's insane that you were you were
commuting from San Francisco to Menel
Park, so that's like almost an hour in
each direction. And you said you were
working 16 to 18 hours a day, about 7
days a week. I can't imagine what that
was like. One of the learnings from your
your note is that you should find work
that you care about deeply. I still
wonder were there times where you were
thinking I you care about the work but
that just as a human I can't imagine
surviving that kind of work schedule. I
mean, I I it probably wasn't 16 to 18
every day, but you know, it was was
working a lot for sure. And and I
definitely sacrificed other parts of my
life. Like I used to be a very serious
rock climber. I uh was on the US team. I
competed in World Cups and I basically
gave up that part of my my life, you
know, for sure in that time. Um, but it
was also such a unique opportunity to
like be able to build this thing that
was just going to go out to hundreds of
millions of people. And uh, you know,
one of the things I loved most when I
was working on Instagram is I'd be like
riding the Cal Train and I'd look over
someone's shoulder and I'd see them
using the thing I just built like a week
before and like that was such a cool
experience. So, uh, yeah, it was like,
you know, you sacrifice certain things,
but I was kind of happy to do so. Uh,
definitely not a sustainable model. So,
I wouldn't, you know, I wouldn't
recommend
doing that over a long period of time,
but in in stints, it can it can make
sense. And I think by
doing that work with that intensity, it
it paid dividends later on. So um the
stories Instagram stories product came
out. It was much better executed I think
than some of the other stories efforts
at the company. There were ones
happening in Facebook and in in
Messenger. I think part of that was just
the care that we put into it. It
contributed to its success. I think the
reception on launch was very positive. I
actually was really worried about it. I
thought the whole thing was just going
to crash and burn just because I could
see all these cracks in it. You know,
you you see the crash reports, you see
all the bugs, like you're kind of your
own harshest critic. But then when it
went out, people were like, "Wow, this
is so polished." And I was like,
"Really? Are we using the same thing?"
Um, but uh yeah, it was it was nice to
have that reception. And uh so I think
it helped the product. And then you know
personally for my career having kind of
demonstrated that I could deliver this
project on a on a tight timeline uh with
this level of craft helped me get on to
you know the most interesting projects
going forward. I saw at the end of the
note it says you you started at IC4 at
Instagram and you got to IC6 by the end
of you know after this gauntlet of these
projects of white out and stories.
That's incredible. Like one promo per
half for two halves straight. What was
that like?
>> There's a bit bit of a funny story. Um
so the promotion cycle happened in July.
We we shipped stories at the beginning
of August. So calibrations were kind of
happening in in July and so we were in
the middle of this like very intense
project and I think like the there was a
lot of recognition of how hard we were
working. I think the managers like they
were being cautious around us and I knew
so I I felt fairly confident that I'd
been misleled on higher. I just wasn't
that familiar with levels when I came in
and I kind of looked around and I was
like, you know, I'm executing a lot
higher than I IC4.
um my Android counterpart uh who was an
incredible engineer, Will Bailey, he was
sort of the tech lead for the whole
stories uh project and he really like
set the example for me of like how you
could be a successful product engineer
and he was incredible at getting me into
the meetings and you know being in the
room with Mike and Kevin as we made all
the decisions. So he was an IC8. So I
kind of like, you know, we he certainly
had a bigger role on the project, but we
had some somewhat similar roles and was
like, "Okay, I'm you're at IC4, you're
at IC8." Um, and so that kind of opened
my eyes to to some of the leveling
stuff. So I told my manager at the time,
Eddie, uh, he he was he was the
director. So I was reporting to the
director just um because uh you know
it's kind of a unique project at the
company and I was like hey I think I got
misleled and I think you should promote
me from four to six in this cycle.
>> Wow.
>> And uh to his credit like he didn't just
totally brush me off and be like you
know just dismiss it. He he said he
actually went and talked to HR about it
and they came back and they were like,
"We've done this twice in the history of
the company. In both cases, it worked
out terribly. The the people left um you
know, very quickly." Uh so he was like
he's like, "We're not going to do it."
But I kind of wanted to seed a little
bit that like, you know, probably the
correct level for me is is a higher IC6.
Um, and I knew it was unlikely that they
were just going to do that one step. Um,
but I I had a guess that like if I was
just on that normal cycle, you know, it
would come up the next time and they'd
be like, well, he just got promoted last
half like um you know, we we can wait.
Uh, and I think it's good for people to
recognize that ultimately these levels
and promotions, they're an incentive
system. I think in the long run like
there's really an effort to make it
fair. Um, but there's also an element of
like it's the carrot that's being
dangled in front of you, right? And so
it can actually make sense even if
somebody's performing at a higher level
that like the promotion gets delayed um
just so that they're not happening in
quick succession. So I kind of wanted to
like seed the idea that like you should
probably probably get me to six pretty
soon here. Um so yeah they they uh you
know the first half on um white out the
redesign and some of the infrastructure
stuff I got the IC5 promotion and then
uh the six came for stories.
>> It's interesting you say like your high
performance I mean you know of course
the promotions are one thing but one of
the things that you took away personally
was that it gave you freedom to work on
whatever projects you wanted. How does
that play out?
>> Yeah, I think it's just like
demonstrated that like, you know, if you
put me on a project, I'm going to do a
good job with it. And so when there is a
new effort at the company, you know,
it's just kind of a natural like, okay,
let's take the people that have done
well on the new efforts before. And um
yeah, so I mean I was very lucky to to
have the opportunity, but then like
executing well on it set me up well for
the future.
>> Yeah. you already left before the
Instagram threads, but I noticed a
similar model which is you pull together
all the the top Instagram people and you
got this small kind of similar like the
stories team and you know all those
people have proven themselves
repeatedly. So
>> and it's a very fun environment to be a
part of that kind of team. The next
promotion actually came from IGTV which
my understanding it's like a I mean I
was at the company at the time so it's
kind of like a YouTube clone almost or
like but vertical video first in
Instagram. Could you talk about that
project that got you promoted to IC7 or
senior staff?
>> So it was very much like uh uh came from
Kevin the CEO him and Ian Sber who's
another amazing designer. They before
like an end of year all hands had um
kind of designed this thing together
laid out this vision for uh Instagram
getting into
kind of longer form video was was the
pitch and it was going to be mobile
native so it was going to be vertical
the way that you hold your phone and uh
so they came actually with like a fairly
developed vision to all hands and kind
of surprised guys presented it to
everybody. It's like here's what we're
going to do. Yeah, I I saw that and
again I was like I got to work on this
thing. This looks cool. It ended up
being a bit of a weird project in the
beginning because um yeah, it was like
the surprise reveal. If you read through
some of the recent antitrust uh
litigation with Facebook, there's some
insights into tensions between Facebook
and Instagram during this time. like we
were told not to work on it for for a
while was kind of like the end of the
founders time at Instagram. IGTV was
kind of like the last thing that they or
last major thing they were there for. Um
but it was again a really cool group,
very small team. Myself, Will Bailey,
Thomas Dimpson, um and uh you know kind
of like iOS, Android and um server
leads. And then we each had like one or
two other uh people per platform
and uh yeah just like super talented
group um great engineers, great
designers. Uh we moved super quickly. I
mean the product doesn't exist anymore
today. it didn't it didn't end up doing
that well. And it's kind of interesting
to reflect on why I think like it had
some things that uh ended up becoming
the future like vertical video is very
much a thing today. Um but it was kind
of trying to mix like this long form
YouTube style content into this vertical
format and maybe that was a bit of a
mismatch. Uh people just weren't
producing highquality long form in the
vertical format. We tried some
interesting AI techniques to take
landscape content and reformat it for
vertical. I've got a patent on that.
That's kind of one of my more
interesting patents. Um but uh we showed
that to create video creators and they
were like horrified. They were like,
"You're destroying my content. Like why?
I've spent so long making this nice
landscape video now. You've just ruined
it." So, we tried to push people to
produce this original long- form
vertical video. And I think the
inventory just never really showed up.
And there was maybe a little bit of
hubris. It was like, you know, Instagram
can just change the industry. We can
just people will just start making this
because we have this platform, this
audience. And that didn't totally
materialize. So, I think it probably did
inform a lot of like, you know, what
ultimately shipped as as reals. Um but
uh yeah, IGTV itself didn't didn't
totally work out.
>> Yeah, I was cuz I was working on the
like video infrastructure team at the
time. So actually that was one of the
things that I got plugged into at some
point. I remember the energy in the San
Francisco office and the war rooms etc.
>> Yeah, totally.
>> You mentioned antitrust and what's the
antirust component you're talking about?
a lot of the sort of internal
communication has now become public
through this antirust uh lawsuit where
um the Justice Department I think is is
suing Facebook to unwind the Instagram
acquisition. Um, and so certain things
that were kind of confusing to me at the
time, like why why were certain things
happening, um, are less confusing now
that I read some of the the internal
communications that was previously
private, including private to me. You
know, I didn't I wasn't exposed, uh, to
it. But, um, yeah, I mean, I think
basically
Instagram, you know, had been acquired.
It was it was smaller,
certainly small relative to Facebook and
then had gone through several years of
just incredible growth and now was kind
of more of like a peer to Facebook and
was kind of like the new popular kid
terms of like you know the Instagram
stories was received better than the
stories in Facebook. And so I think that
created some tension between the
Instagram leadership and the Facebook
leadership. And there was concerns about
Instagram cannibalizing or taking users
from Facebook. Um
which yeah just kind of guided some of
the the
strategy decisions I guess. I remember
that too because I was I mean I was also
on the Instagram team and I remember
there was some confusion about you know
why are we turning off the I guess
somehow like followers were being
forwarded from Facebook to Instagram or
was like cross sharing or something like
the direction from Facebook to Instagram
was getting turned off or something like
that and yeah I think I read the same
thing you read because I was like oh
this makes so much sense it's like Mark
Zuckerberg's internal memo on you know
all of that and all the tensions between
you know the Instagram founders Mark and
he's saying
>> he wants to keep them and they're great
at building products but you know he's
like trying to navigate his side of the
equation. Super interesting.
>> It'd be really interesting to know how
you know how he thinks about it today.
Uh that was now seven years ago.
>> Mark or the Instagram founders? Mark. Um
because I sense in those communications
like something of a very understandable
emotional attachment to the Facebook
product, right? This was like kind of
the thing that he created and Instagram.
He deserves all the credit for acquiring
it, but it was a little bit less his
thing. Um,
and yeah, I just wonder, uh, does he
view that differently today than he did
now? Uh, you know, seven years on, um,
he owns both of these things. Um, I
always had the view that like the best
the way to get the best outcome for the
overall company was actually to have
these things compete with each other
because it's like you own both. they're
going to make each other better and you
know one of them will win versus like if
you don't if you kind of stifle that
competition
somebody from the outside is like more
likely to come up with something better
and and take over. Um but uh yeah I
don't know I mean he's the one running a
multi-trillion dollar company and I'm
not so arm armchair CEOing over here.
>> Yeah. Maybe one day if this podcast
scales up and I ever have Mark on, I'll
I'll ask him that.
>> And then lastly at Instagram, I know you
started a group called IG Labs. I'm
curious the story behind you starting
that group and I also understand this is
your promo to IC8 or like director
equivalent at Instagram. So yeah, what's
the story behind IGLabs? after IGTV. Um,
definitely spent some time like Thomas
Simpson has this phrase like wandering
the impact desert like just looking for
for things to do and and not necessarily
finding anything great. Um, and I was
actually pretty close to to leaving the
company at that time. Um,
and kind of the new effort became reals
and I didn't feel good about working on
like passive video consumption. Um, my
manager was was over the reals or so, so
it, you know, would have made sense for
me to work on it, but I was I was fairly
certain I I I didn't want to work on
that. I I helped the team a bit, but
like um yeah, it wasn't going to be my
project. Through that time, there was a
lot of like culture change. the founders
had left. Um, you know, the leadership
kind of came over from Facebook,
uh, the new leadership. Um, a lot of
kind of like the old Instagram culture,
it felt like was being kind of pushed
out.
And I was talking with like the the new
head of engineering um
about trying to bring back some of that
energy that I think had made product
development at Instagram special, small
teams, attention to craft, uh and also
really expanding
kind of the
the scope of what we worked on. So, you
know, we were very focused on like the
existing Instagram app and the existing
features within Instagram and just kind
of like iterative features on that, very
like incremental improvements. And I
kind of made this pitch that like we
have this great brand um we could do
other things under the Instagram brand
like let's let's go try that. let's, you
know, explore like location ideas, maps
ideas, uh, places. Um, and again, paire
paired with a really awesome designer,
uh, Vivian Wong. And, um, we, yeah, made
the pitch to to start this team. It was
just her and myself in the beginning.
And uh the idea was just to have kind of
this like Delta Force like small group,
very high talent density that would work
on new product initiatives and things
that just didn't slot cleanly into the
org. Like Instagram had grown to such a
size where you really needed like a lot
of structure in the org just to keep
things sane. But that meant that
projects that like didn't slot cleanly
into one of those orgs were probably
underinvested in. And so part of the
idea of this team was that we would span
across, you know, we wouldn't have a
focus area. We could kind of work work
across many things. Um
we we tried a lot. I mean, a lot of it
didn't ship or tested. Um, probably one
of the more lasting impactful things, it
it seems small, but I think it actually
gets used quite a bit is the
collaborative post feature where uh you
can have multiple authors on a post. Um,
it's another of the more interesting
patents I have is is on that one. Um and
uh and so yeah, I think I think we found
good impact and then we were also this
concentration of talent that like when
there was a new important initiative
ultimately ended up being threads um you
had this group that that could go work
on it and uh and yeah just trying to uh
I don't know kind of encourage
innovation trying new things and and
push that at the company. The last thing
at your on your Instagram journey was
that you tried management at some point
or as an ICA you switched to I guess
TLDD or tech lead director. What was
your thinking behind that and how'd it
go?
>> It's a very unusual or rare role within
Facebook. Um even like TLM I think is
quite rare or was at the time um than
like tech lead director probably even
even more so. Um,
it kind of happened mostly because I had
started this group and at some point it
just made a lot more sense for me to
manage the people in that group rather
than my manager who was over the reals
or um just less connected to to their
work. You know, I could probably
represent them better in calibrations. I
mean, I was in the calibrations anyways,
so I was kind of like doing a lot of
this work. So um yeah, in some ways it
was just kind of like a formal
recognition of like what I was doing
already. Um to to have these people
report to me. Um Facebook is is very
much of the school of thought of like
individual contributors and management
should be separate and I don't subscribe
to that. Um, other companies work
differently. Like my wife is a senior
staff engineer at Tesla and like um
they're very flexible. It's like
IC's have people report to them all the
time. Um, managers are expected to be
like pretty competent uh technical
contributors and like doing individual
contributions.
Um, and I think I prefer that model. Um,
and so it was interesting for me to to
try it. I think like another one of my
sort of controversial opinions is like I
think senior engineers should be
involved in coding. Um, there's overlap
between that thought and like the
thought that like um managers should be
still somewhat involved.
There's
an author I I really like, Nasim Talb.
Um and he talks about having skin in the
game and um yeah, I think like if you're
a senior IC who has to do some coding,
like you have more skin in the game.
Like you're not going to come up with
some architecture that like you just
hand off to somebody else and it's their
problem now, right? Like you're going to
be involved. You're going to see more
hands-on what the issues are. Um, and I
think like similarly like if you're
managing a team and you're much more
like with them in the day-to-day stuff,
uh, I think that you will operate
better. So, um, yeah, it's, you know,
maybe a bit against the grain at
Facebook. Um, but it was a philosophy I
had and I wanted to to try it out. Um,
and then there was an upside to it as
well in a company that grew so much and
was so big where
at Facebook the levels are are private,
right? So you're just a software
engineer through through your whole IC
time. And in some ways I like that for
like engineering discussions that
there's no like pulling of rank like hey
I'm more senior you know just take my
idea like it's a little bit more
meritocratic perhaps but in cross
functional situations say you're working
with like a PM like I'm trying to ship
this um collaborative post thing and I
have to like meet with PM all these
different PMs on these different teams.
Um, there was an element where having a
little bit higher of a title I think
just made those conversations easier.
Like I had a higher baseline where they
were like, "Okay, this person like maybe
they like know something. They they've
been here a bit like they're not just
um, you know, totally new." And um you
know you you build up some reputation in
a company but when it gets so big and
there's new people joining all the time
like you're actually having to like
reestablish that a lot with with folks.
So um yeah I think like it it it was
somewhat helpful to have that title.
There would be discussions in the in the
senior engineering group about like
should should there be some form of of
public levels um within the company and
I was supportive of like maybe like a
two maybe not like the full level is is
public but like there's like a senior
designation or something. Um just uh
yeah I think largely for like when
you're working with people outside of
your normal working group so that they
start from a slightly better baseline on
you know whether whether you know what
you're talking about. The number one
thing I hear people say is the this is
not optimal because it's you're doing
two jobs at once and you're gonna drown
and your career will not flourish in
either direction. What do you say to
that? I think it's probably correct.
Like um at that point I was really not
optimizing for career. Um you know it
was never my intent to stay longterm.
Uh I I mentioned this in the career note
like Facebook does these internal
employee sentiment surveys every 6
months I think or year and one of the
questions on there is how long do you
intend to to stay with the company. I
never put more than one year. It was
always like okay this is my last year
I'm going to I'm going to get out soon.
Um, and so yeah, I think like I didn't
have aspirations to get to IC9. Um, and
so it kind of freed me up where it was
like, you know, um, well, I don't want
to get fired for performance, but I kind
of knew I wasn't going to get fired for
performance. Um, and so, yeah, there was
just a little bit less pressure on that.
and um yeah, so I could just kind of
like do the thing that made sense for
our group, our team um and and worry a
little bit less about the career stuff.
But yeah, absolutely. I think like I saw
firsthand like I think my ratings were
probably lower than they would have been
if I was just an IC maybe. Um
it was like okay you're exceeding as an
IC but you're meeting as a manager so
you're just meeting
>> you know that's kind of like the full
journey from you know start to finish of
Instagram and I know you you've left
you've since left and you're working on
retro which is a popular social media
app with a lot of the polish that I kind
of recognize in Instagram as well. I'm
curious you know what made you want to
leave to start that? what's the story
behind creating retro?
>> So, around the last few months of my
time there, I was talking with Nathan,
who's my my co-founder. Um, we had
worked on stories together. He had gone
over to the Facebook side. He started
Facebook dating. Uh, and then he was
working on some of the virtual reality
products. And through our whole time,
you know, we were close friends. We
would meet up at this bar sometimes in
the mission called Lone Palm and we
would talk about how we just saw a
different way to build products to
structure a company and you know we
really wanted to be in the driver's seat
of that and uh we would talk about
starting a company but it was always
like that the timing wasn't right for
me. I was on a project that I was
engaged on and then I'd be like okay I
think I'm ready and he was on something
new. Um, and so finally our our timing
kind of aligned um where we were both
ready to leave and I had a conversation
with um this investor friend, the same
one that connected me with Flipboard
who's he's kind of a mentor of mine and
um he was like it's time you should you
should really take a bet on yourself and
and that stuck with me. I was like yeah
I should like take a bet on myself. Um,
and so we left to start the company. And
actually our our goal with the company
is really to create this world-class
product studio. And Retro is our first
product, but it's not necessarily like
uh the reason for the company existing.
And we yeah, we just want to kind of
create this environment where great
product builders can do the best work of
their lives. and create products that
are good for people that they feel good
after using um and and also to create a
successful business. Uh so retro is our
is our first product and it's a social
app but it's actually quite different
from what are called the social apps
today I would say um in that it's
actually social you you you see people
you know on it uh friends it's it's all
focused around friends and um you know
I'd say like the traditional social
media is maybe well the derogatory word
I would say is like brain brain brain
rot media. Um, entertainment is maybe
like a more favorable uh term, but if I
open Instagram today, I don't see a lot
of the people I know. Um, even if I
actually go to seek that out, I tend to
end up down a rabbit hole of uh kind of
short form video entertaining content.
And um, it's definitely entertaining,
but it it kind of hijacks my attention.
I get sucked into it. And so the idea
behind Retro is we're creating a space
that's all about connecting with the
people that you actually know, staying
up to date with them, and also
appreciating your own life by looking
back on your photos and kind of picking
out the highlights. And in some ways,
it's a throwback to kind of the earlier
times in social media, what Instagram
used to be, all about creation. Um,
almost half of the people that use retro
on a daily basis actually post
something. Um, which you know I know
from working at Instagram that like that
number is quite a bit lower. Um, and I
take it as a really good sign that we
have created a product where people show
up to create almost as much as they show
up to consume. Uh, so we've been working
on that for the past few years. Um, it's
uh become very popular in Taiwan.
>> Oh, interesting. which is not something
we expected, but um you know, social
networks are so much about the network,
whether your friends get on it and we we
managed to hit the critical mass in
Taiwan and sort of all of the usage
patterns end up looking different when
when you hit that critical mass. Um so
we were number one on the app store
there for a period last uh last year. Um
and we still are at the top of the of
the photo category. We were number two
when I looked this morning. Um, so we've
kind of shown that like it when it
works, it works. Um, and we had just
have this challenge of making it work in
more places. And um, you it's very
challenging to get people to try a new
app. Um, but if you miss seeing your
friends and people you know on social
media and staying connected with them, I
you know, very much encourage you to uh
to try out Retro. And uh and yeah, it's
I I think it's a a really delightful
app. I love seeing photos from my family
on there. And uh and we want it to feel
good when you open it and feel good when
you close it. So you don't feel like
your attention was hijacked that you
feel like this was a good use of time.
You got caught up with the people you
care about and then you can go on with
your life. You can get out and enjoy the
world. the design philosophy you went
for with this app. Is it more
challenging to get people to use it
because it's less addictive?
>> So, one of the key decisions that we've
designed around is that we don't have an
adbased business model. Um, and I
actually I don't think like ads are
evil, but I I do think that ads when
combined with an algorithmic feed are a
little bit evil. Um, because you have
this misaligned incentive. Um, you know,
I think the app is incentivized for you
to just consume more and more. It just
wants more and more of your time and
attention.
um even past, you know, what you wanted
to get out of the app. I show up to see
what a friend is doing, it's going to
try to keep me there for the next hour,
2 hours, whatever. Uh and so I I think
ads fundamentally kind of like when
combined with an algorithmic feed um
make products that aren't super aligned
with people. Uh but there there is
definitely a challenge uh in terms of
like growing retro. So you know we don't
have uh creators the the model is mutual
friending. So um everyone is private.
You can only see people that you've uh
accepted as friends and has to go both
ways. It's not like a following model.
And we have a limit of 250 friends. And
so, um, you can't build an audience on
this platform. And so, a lot of the ways
that like Instagram grew was through
creators that were financially
incentivized to spread this app and get
more followers. And so, those those
pathways to growth are not open to us.
Um, but we've we've seen examples of
like, you know, Bal uh managed to get a
decent growth. They had kind of a nice
viral uh mechanic built in with this
notification that everyone got that was
weird. It's time to be real. You know,
that created a lot of conversation. So,
that certainly helped. Um, but I think
it is possible to to grow a friends only
uh social network, but in many ways it
is it is harder and and also the
business model is is harder. Um, that's
something that that we're very open
about like this is a challenge. um there
would be easier ways to do things, but
we think they would lead to bad
outcomes, outcomes we don't want in the
long term. We're very much taking an
opinion on what this product should be
and what we want to see in the world. Um
you know, some people say just just
build what people want and you know,
maybe you could say like in Instagram
people are demonstrating that it's what
they want cuz they spend more of their
time there. Um, and we're taking a
little bit more of an opinionated stance
saying no, we think like actually that's
not great and this is better and even if
it's more challenging, it's something we
strongly believe should exist in the
world and should be an option there for
for people that want it. Um, I think we
also actually coexist really nicely
alongside Instagram. Like I still have
it. I still open it. Um, but I'm getting
sucked into it a lot less and it's
helped me kind of break this like phone
addiction that um, yeah, I just I didn't
feel good about.
>> How do you monetize if you're not using
ads?
>> We have a a subscription, a premium
subscription and um, so it's only a
small percentage of users that are
subscribers and it's just kind of like
an extra tier of features particularly
some of the things that cost us a lot to
provide as a service. So video as you
know from video infrastructure like the
storage and bandwidth for that is quite
a bit more than than photos. Um and so
you have to subscribe if you want to
share out video. Uh but the free version
of the app is like actually great. Um
you know uh you can share photos, you
can remember your own life. Um and it's
like 93% of what people share on retro
is photos anyways. Um, and uh, and so,
um, yeah, if you want to kind of like
support the mission and and get those
extra features, you can become a
subscriber.
>> That's awesome. I love like the
intention behind it and like the the
mission. It's really cool.
>> It's definitely a product that's fun to
work on. It feels good like Yeah, it's
it's very a very feel-good. We had a
tagline for a while like feel good
social media and um yeah it's very much
that
>> coming from big tech and starting your
own company. I'm curious like looking
back on you know across the various
career axes of maybe like you know
learning
satisfaction compensation
you know the things that people look at
for their career. How has it been so far
working on your own thing?
>> Yeah um compensation is quite a bit
worse.
We we pay Nathan and I pay ourselves
less than all of our employees and we
have more ownership in the in the
company which I think is the right way.
It's how it should be. Um uh but that
means that yeah, you know, kind of um
certainly put off that short-term
compensation. We hope to become a very
successful company and that that equity
is going to be worth a lot both for us
and for our employees. It was always the
thing I wanted to do. Like I I I was a
bit surprised actually that I ended up
in in in big tech, you know, talking
about like those early days in in
Flipboard and um kind of this like
entrepreneurial culture. Like it was
always exciting to me. I would read
TechCrunch all the time um about the new
startups and uh yeah, I just always
wanted to kind of build a company, you
know, be able to to bring the best
people together, work on the things that
we thought were cool. Um do the things
do things in the way that we wanted to
do them. And uh yeah, it's been it's
been awesome for that. Um, and uh, and
definitely like have learned a ton. I
think the amount of time that I get to
spend on interesting work is much higher
than it was, especially in my later
years at Instagram. Like a lot of my
work became kind of like convincing
uh, you know, layers above me that we
should do something. I I would say there
were probably more people working on
that app than there needed to be. And so
actually there was a lot of gatekeeping
um where it was like is your team
allowed to ship? So you would do this
work and then there was like you have to
convince somebody that like this is a
good enough thing for to ship in the
product which is understandable because
you know it becomes very complex if you
just let everybody go. But it means that
there's a lot of work in just kind of
like that political wrangling and like
how do I how do I make this person feel
like this is their idea, not my idea. Um
and and I'd spend none of my time on
that now. Um you know, we we do a 1-hour
standup uh every day. That's basically
the only meeting uh on my calendar. So,
um, I get almost the whole day to to
just, uh, build, think about, you know,
what people want and and try to make it.
Um, so, um, yeah, I'd say like
satisfaction is definitely higher. Um,
learning is definitely higher,
compensation is definitely lower.
I
>> I think throughout the conversation you
mentioned that, you know, smaller teams
can move faster. Do you think that the
company would be better off if you just
like laid off half the people?
>> I was I would say yes. We we used to
talk about this a lot when the company
was much smaller. Um like uh this
thought experiment of like you know the
Thanos like you just snap your fingers
like half of people are fired even if
it's a random selection um do things go
better and frequently we felt like yeah
maybe I think they would. Um, so yeah.
Um, I mean it's tough because with a
business like Instagram, you know, if
you can make a.1% improvement, it's
actually like hundreds of millions of
dollars to to the business. And so
sometimes um, you know, that incremental
person maybe they they're able to find
those things. Uh, but I think it's less
appreciated the cost of each person you
add. And there's sort of like maybe the
more obvious just organizational
communication overhead. You know, you
you just have more stakeholders, more
meetings, more coordination.
But um even just like writing more code,
like having more code in the app. Um I
remember right before I left, they had
this tool where you could see how much
time you were spending compiling the
app. Um, and I was spending more than
four hours a day waiting for the app to
build just because there was so much
code and you know the tooling just had
not kept up with basically the the
velocity at which people were writing
code and uh so that's a huge cost that's
kind of you know it's not noticeable
with each incremental person you have
but now you have this you have a
thousand engineers and all of a sudden
like everyone's just like so slowed down
because uh yeah because of this
overhead. So um yeah with a with a
smaller team you know like when we were
10 people and the app was tiny it was
like so much easier to get things done
like a project like like white out um
you know would be like a massive project
for Instagram today because there's so
many more surfaces there's so much more
code there's so many more people was
actually like a lot easier at the time
that I did it. Yeah, I guess you know
Twitter is kind of an interesting case
study of that because they kind of did
went through that and the the app's
still operating. I do get the sense that
there's a lot more breakages, but I'd be
curious like on the product development
side, you know, is it how has that been
being on those teams?
>> Totally. Yeah. I mean, I think there
were projections when Elon came in and I
think he cut like 80%
>> Yeah.
>> of the staff or people left as well,
>> right? that like, oh, this thing was
just going to 100% fall over. Um, and I
mean, my experience is somewhat buggy.
There's definitely some issues. Um, but
I mean, you know, it's very much
continuing to to run. I think also I saw
like the economics of the business have
actually become much better. Um, it's
actually profitable now. uh whereas you
know through almost its entire history
it was operating at quite a loss and so
um yeah somebody coming in and and with
a machete cutting things like may maybe
it's okay
>> towards the end of the conversation I
just want to wrap up with a few career
reflections I think first thing is you
throughout your projects you worked with
like a lot of very talented people I
think you mentioned you know Thomas
Dimpson will Bailey a few incredible
designers. Also, sounds like you worked
with the founders of Instagram. And I'm
curious, do you have any stories that
you share that illustrate what made them
exceptional?
>> Mike Kger is is definitely something of
a of a hero of mine and it was like such
a privilege to to get to work with him.
They they say like don't meet your
heroes because you'll be disappointed,
but I think like you should meet Mike
Creger. He's he's actually an awesome
human and um a lot of the ways that I
think about
engineering leadership and engineering
philosophy came from him. Uh so I
mentioned earlier the simple thing
first, you know, that's really stuck
with me. I think the attention to detail
and craft. Um, but another thing is he
had this sort of I don't know if it was
intentional or just the way he is, but
it was like this lead from the front uh
or I call it like lead from the front
way of operating where he never put
himself above the team and he would just
jump in to whatever team if an effort
needed help. So uh at the end of stories
I had brought in a friend of mine from
Flipboard actually who was then working
at Facebook not at Instagram very
different team to do the drawing tools
just because he had worked on a drawing
app before and I was like hey we need
drawing like can you work on this um
it's kind of a an interesting insight
into like how Facebook operates that I
could just like go to this random you
know person on a very different part of
the or and pull him in to this project.
Um, so he worked on it for a few weeks
and and got it reasonably far, but uh
then kind of got pulled back by his
team. Um, so we were in we were in a bit
of a pickle and um Mike just came in and
was like, "Okay, I'll I'll finish it."
Like um so he, you know, he's in there
coding the the neon brush and uh you
know, we were working those insane
hours. He was there working them with
us. Um he's up at 2 am reviewing my
diffs. Um, and uh, yeah, just seeing
that and how that felt as a team uh,
really has informed like the way I think
about leading teams. Um, and and so
yeah, that he he's he's awesome. Um,
some of the other folks you mentioned,
Will Bailey, I talked about him a little
bit before. He has just this product
vision that he sticks to very strongly
and frequently it's quite good. He at
the kind of like I would say like dark
days of development of the stories
project when it was spinning in circles.
It was taking different forms. None of
them felt very good. He just kind of
outlined this full vision in a document
for like how this product should work.
um you know the things that we could do
with it going forward. And I looked back
on it five years later and I was like,
"Wow, this was like the five-year road
map for for what we ended up doing."
Like he basically nailed it all from the
start. Um and uh and yeah, he was such a
good example for like how you could
succeed as a product focused engineer.
Um which actually was fairly it it was
much more of a thing in Instagram than
it was in Facebook. I remember being in
boot camp and people were saying okay if
you're junior you go work on a product
team and then if you're senior you work
on an infrastructure team and that was
kind of the culture was like you know
product is easy but like you know real
engineers they work on infrastructure
and uh and Instagram actually
prioritized more in some ways the the
product side and I think that was
reflected in you know the various
versions of stories for example um And
so Will was such a great kind of mentor
and um example of like how you could
have this successful career as a as a
product engineer. Um how you could
influence product direction as an
engineer. And then Thomas is uh is
probably just like the smartest person
I've ever met. Like he's he he's
incredibly smart, but not in like a
savant kind of way. like he's also like
you know uh got great social still
skills and understands people um and uh
so he did the feed ranking or you know
basically started all the ranking at
Instagram um he started his own company
open a open AI bought his company he's a
researcher there now maybe Zuck's coming
to him with a$und00 million offer I
don't know um but uh but yeah again like
you know he actually had like this skill
on the infrastructure side. Um, you
know, built a lot of the infrastructure
for the ranking stuff, but always
approached it with a product mindset and
and I think would probably consider
himself like a product person. Um, I
have always been interested in
technology as like a means to
create things for people. Um, I've never
been that interested in like the
technology itself. Um, it's like only
interesting to me to the extent that
like I can create interesting
experiences for people. Uh so yeah, I
think like um Thomas and and Will
um you know kind of had maybe a similar
approach very like humanoriented
um thinking about the psychology how
people use these things and how it makes
them feel. And then you know last
question is if you could go back to
yourself after all this experience that
you have and talk to yourself when you
were just graduating college and give
yourself some career advice what would
you say
>> like just invest in the tools of your
time to build things for people like
build products for people and I think if
you if you do that you'll be pretty
flexible and adaptable and in many ways
you have a unique opportunity as a new
grad because you you aren't sort of
stuck on this path of like I'm I'm an
iOS person. I know this technology
really well. Like it's all new to you
and so you can pick up the latest thing,
right? And so I think like with these AI
tools that are coming out um you can do
incredible things with them and you're
probably going to be more skilled at
those than the senior engineers um
because it's just not the thing that
they you know learned natively that
they've invested their time into. And I
had that to some extent with iOS where
it was a it was a newer thing and so
like the senior engineers were like
writing Java or something you know they
were writing our back end and I could
actually stand out and excel on this
thing because it was the first thing I
learned and um you know I was eager
hungry and uh I think there's there's
something to that with like this new set
of AI tools. So yeah, I think my advice
for new grads is just like you learn the
tools of your time and and and get good
at them and and make things make good
things for people. Um, and I think I
think that will work out. I imagine it's
it's a bit scary probably because it's
hard to say how it's going to play out,
but like it seems like there's reducing
demand for like junior software
engineers because of some of these AI
tools. But I think if you can yourself
get really good at using those tools,
there will definitely be roles for you.
>> Awesome. Well, yeah, thank you so much
for your time, Ryan. I was really um
yeah, you're a legend at Instagram and I
worked there for so long. Super excited
to talk to you at this point. Is there
anything you want to redirect the
audience attention to?
>> If the ideas behind Retro sound
interesting to you, um definitely try it
out. Um it's, you know, it's a great
place to to reconnect with people that
you you uh want to see into their lives,
but maybe they've stopped posting on
social media. So, so get them on, too.
If you're a designer, you're an
engineer, um definitely reach out. I
think we have some interesting ideas in
in how we're building this company. You
know, I mentioned before our goal is to
become a world-class product studio.
multiple products. We have um Retro, we
have two more in the pipeline right now.
And I think we have some interesting
ways we're structuring revenue share
with employees. So, as these apps start
to make money, um even if the company's
ambition is to kind of like take that
and reinvest it into growth, um you can
see some of that upside right away. And
we're building infrastructure that helps
support products across the portfolio.
So, we're building growth tools,
analytics tools, all of that, um, that I
think are going to really help us excel
as a product studio. So, if that's
interesting to you, you know, reach out
for a conversation. And, uh, yeah, it's
just been a pleasure chatting and thanks
for having me on.
>> Thanks so much, Ryan. Really appreciate
your time.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to